Okay, so let's talk about the scope
statement now.
Now, the scope statement is an important
artifact, and it is a detailed document,
right?
But it's like a summary
of the deliverable, if you
like, the summary of
what this project is about.
So think of it as more of a detailed
summary about the project.
So it's going to have a detailed
description of what we're delivering,
right, the detailed description.
so, you know, that basically relates to
the product scope, right, and the work
required to create the deliverable,
right, which is the project scope.
Now, when we say the
work required, we're not
talking about individual
activities, right?
The scope statement does not include,
like, work packages, activities,
team members, or who's working on what
activity, right?
We haven't gotten down to that granular
level yet, right?
This is just basically showing what the
project is, what we are delivering,
and really kind of like the constraints
around them.
I think of it as a requirement, so
then all of the constraints around them.
So it's going to include the product scope
as well as the project scope.
So it's going to include then what the
main scope of the project is, what the
project is about basically the objective
of the project, is going to include what
the major deliverables
are, any assumptions and
constraints that you're
going to be making, right?
It's also going to contain the acceptance
criteria, what is included,
what is excluded.
So as a very, very high-level simple
example, just think of building house, right?
So you want to build a house, right?
So a scope statement would include,
right, the very first section,
if you like, would be the objective.
And the objective would
have what the project
is and then what the
major constraints are.
So an objective could be something like,
for example, scope of the project is to
build a single family home
or a modern single family
home within 10 months and
with a budget of $500,000.
Just as a very simple example.
So you've got the objective, building a
modern single family home.
And then you've got the
budget constraint, $500,000
and the scheduling
constraint within 10 months.
So that's the main objective of your
project.
And then you would further go into a
little bit more detail, right?
You go into more detail.
What are the main requirements,
right?
So it has to be, for example, a five
bedroom house, five bathrooms, right?
The kitchen also has to have like a
utility room or a utility kitchen.
You have to have a buttless pantry.
That's to be 4,000 square feet.
Right.
And then you're going to further add other
deliverables assumptions, right?
So it needs to meet, you know,
this particular building code.
So what are the building code
requirements, for example, for,
you know, for the electrical, for the
plumbing, for the heating, insulation.
So it's going to contain all of the basic
constraints as well, the
other major constraint.
What is included, what is excluded.
So what is included is, you know,
maybe laying down grass, right,
in the front and the backyard,
in the front garden, back garden.
But what included is actually planting as
a very simple example also what might be
excluded is a full basement right we're
going to create a basement but we're not
going to complete the basement right so
that is excluded then it may contain some
of the assumptions and constraints
constraint might be for example work hours
right so contracting
work or building work can
only be done between
the hours of 8 30 A.M.
and 5 P.M.
Monday to Friday and
because it's in the neighborhood
We don't want to disturb
all of the other neighbours.
And then some of the major milestones.
When are we going to get the permit?
When a building permit is going to be
available?
When our inspection is going to be done?
Are there any specialised equipment,
if you've identified any specialised
equipment that need to be used or any
resources and so and so forth?
Specialised resources.
That would all be included then in the
scope statement.
So at a glance, anybody can
read the scope statement and
have a good understanding
of what the project is about.
You don't necessarily need to be a subject
matter expert, right?
Anybody can read a scope statement and
have a good understanding.
All right, so this is the overall scope of
the project.
I mean, that's really what the scope
statement is.
It contains the requirements and all of
the constraints around the requirements.
But again, it is not going to include any
of the details like team members.
If you need any specialised skill sets or
any specialized equipment, then sure,
that could be documented there.
But it's not going to be documenting any,
you know, who is working on what activity.
It's not going to be documenting any
activities like that.
And the activity list is going to come
much later.
Now, some of the major
tools and techniques then that
we might be using for
creating the scope statement.
Right, well, just like any process that
we're talking about, anything to do with
project management, any
of the project management
procedures, your own
knowledge, right, expert judgment.
If you don't have that
knowledge and experience, then
you're going to reach out
to people that do, right?
So anybody who remember can give you
expert advice.
Now, another tool also in
coming up with the scope of
the project, something
called alternatives analysis.
Right, and alternatives
analysis is something
very popular or rather
something very common.
I see this over and over
again throughout your
project process, and it
is literally as it sounds.
What alternatives are
there to meet, you know,
the same scope of
the project in this case?
So, again, there's a very
simple example, right, while
we're on the subject of,
you know, building a house.
So let's say we've got a building company,
right, building a house, right?
They're building several houses.
And their requirement is we need to build
a 4,000 square foot house.
Well, there's different alternatives.
of the building a four, that's a requirement
building a 4,000 square foot house.
But there are different ways
of meeting that, you know,
different alternative ways
of meeting that requirement.
You could build it all on one level,
there's 4,000 square foot house all on one
level, you could build it on two levels,
you could build it on three levels,
and depending on where this construction
is, if it's in a downtown location,
for example, right, where space is
limited, then more than likely,
I mean, if the requirement is a 4,000
square foot house, more than likely
they'll build it and maybe on three
levels, right?
If you're in a downtown location,
right, the more than likely, you know,
they're talking about a 4,000 square foot
house.
They might build it in three levels,
maybe four levels.
If you're out in the suburb, right,
then you may want to, you know,
the same building company may build it on
two levels.
Or if in a real far suburb,
you know, where land is
plentiful, They might just build
a whole house on one level.
But those are three different
alternatives.
I could build on one level, two level,
three levels, four levels.
But it's achieving the same goal.
You're building a 4,000 square foot house.
And that is literally what alternative
analysis refers to.
Then you've got these other two
multi-criterary decision analysis.
And all multi-critory
refers to the fact that there
are many, many factors
that go into making a decision.
So, you know, when you're coming up with
the scope of the project, Regardless of
what kind of project it is, you're coming
up with the scope of the project.
There might be many, many factors that
impact the scope of the project.
Facilitation just means facilitating
meetings.
And again, these are
one of the interpersonal
skills that is required of
a good project manager.
You're going to be facilitating meetings.
You're going to be facilitating workshops.
You're going to be facilitating focus
groups, brainstorming sessions,
with all of your different stakeholders,
in this case, to understand and come up
with the scope of the project,
to come up with the scope statement.
And then product analysis.
And product analysis is, again,
as it sounds, analyzing the product.
Right.
So breaking the product
down, analyzing it, you
might come across this
term called value engineering.
Right.
So value engineering basically refers to
doing the same work, meeting the same
scope of the project, but without reducing
the cost.
quality, but doing it cheaper.
That is something known as value
engineering.
And in fact, reverse engineering is a type
of product analysis as well.
Looking at your competitors project,
as a very simple example, right?
You're purchasing your competitors product
and then you're breaking it down,
right, to see how they've built it,
right?
And then that could determine,
you know, maybe the scope of your project.
You're doing something very similar.
So you're looking at a
competitive product, breaking
it down, see how they've
built it, what did they use?
And then based on that,
you could come up with
some kind of solution
for your own product.
So the main artifact here then is the
scope statement, right?
And the scope statement then, as I said,
is a detailed document, right?
But just think of it as a detailed
summary, if you like, of the project.
And the detail summary
then is going to include
the product scope as
well as the project scope.
Thank you.